thank you good evening yeah exciting day
watching my daughter take her first but
she's taken the odd step but she
actually walked today
so nice to be back at Findhorn it's
really nice to be in this space and I
must have spent at least a hundred if
not $200 dancing five rhythms on this
floor so some suddenly start spiraling
and stop me yeah let's let's start in
the order of the slides and just very
briefly this is where I come from yeah
New Yorker the reason why I like
starting with this light of planet Earth
is it shows the atmosphere and how thin
that layer of life of biosphere actually
is within which we take our home and
within which everything every love every
war every bit of human history has taken
place and there's not a thing that you
and I can do that doesn't affect the
health and wholeness of this place and
unfortunately we've come through
centuries and millennia of not being
very wise about how we behave within
that living planet we are now in a age
that some people like to call the
Anthropocene where we've become a
geological force we are shaping the
planet and have an enormous impact on
biodiversity on climate change and all
these issues these lights might be
familiar to you this is the planetary
boundaries graphic that shows that we're
already beyond certain planetary
boundaries that if we don't draw back
within the safe limit we might not have
a future and there's lots of things
coming together ecological crises
economic crises social crises and my
friend and mentor Fricke of Capra once
said that if you follow the river of
these crises upstream you meet the
crisis of consciousness a crisis of
perception a crisis of how we see
ourselves and our role in this living
planet
also we're living on an incredibly
unequal planet if you sum up the two
layers of this graph which is produced
by credit Swiss every two years eight
point six percent of humanity on eighty
five point six percent of the wealth
which is staggering but what's even more
staggering is that 71 percent of
humanity have to share 2.7 percent of
the wealth we cannot create a
sustainable planet or a sustainable
future for humanity with this inequity
and we wouldn't want to sustain a
humanity that is that unequal just at
the beginning of this week the IPCC the
panel on climate change released another
report saying while we're completely off
target on what was agreed in Paris with
a two degree target it's actually not
enough we need to radically reduce
carbon emission and actually do more
than that we need to reverse carbon
emission to avoid hothouse earth we're
way on this path and if we don't manage
to take the detour under this same
semi-stable edge we're dropping into
this abyss and a lot of the voices a lot
to two weeks ago the Secretary General
of the United Nations said that we've
got about it a year and a half to take
drastic action
this report again very conservative
talking about twelve years I actually
think we're already in the middle of
what's called runaway climate change
that image up there with the lakes that
that's the permafrost melting that's
these lakes are bubbling like a little
soda pop gassing off gassing Miskin
methane and the circulatory currents in
the oceans are slowing down were
basically faced with is a runaway cycle
now where climate changes getting worse
even
we start paddling back so even if we do
all the things I'm going to be talking
about this evening we are facing three
decades of collapse
but that collapses the collapse of an
old system that no longer serves that we
need to go through in order to give
birth to a new humanity that sees itself
again as part of the community of life
so even if we get everything right we'll
still face three decades of quite severe
upheaval we need to go upstream and look
at this crisis of perception we need to
start thinking about how do we tell the
story of who we are why we are here and
what we could do if we actually lived in
a way that is creating conditions
conducive to life one of my mentors
Janine Benyus the founder of the
biomimicry work says life creates
conditions conducive to life this is in
a nutshell what we should be doing I
would also say that life in a nutshell
is a regenerative community we need to
rejoin that community and to do that we
need to change the stories we tell about
ourselves
and we need to change the organizing
ideas that shape our perception and what
do I mean by that have a look at that
some of you are seeing the head of an
animal some of you are just seeing a
black circle a white circle word with
black dots in it if I give you the
organizing idea head of a giraffe
aha some people go oh I can see it this
is the neck these are the horns this is
the snout the eyes so she she's looking
down this way this is just to show that
organizing ideas are incredibly powerful
we don't see things because they're out
there and they just come in we see
things because we have idea
is about what's out there and we make
the world we bring forth a world
together in conversation and that's the
power of reshaping the world for us as
well one of the big stories that we've
been told is that life is all about
survival of the fittest and the struggle
for survival in on a planet with scarce
resources that's not true
life is a process that acts through
diversification and subsequent
reintegration of that diversity at
higher levels of complexity and more
often than not this is done through new
forms of collaboration this is what we
are challenged to do now we have to and
it seems impossible when we look at the
current news in Brazil in America so
many places we seem to be going in the
exact opposite direction but we have to
this is really let this one sink in we
now have to do the impossible because
the probable is unthinkable and
unconscious unconscionable we have to do
the impossible
so maybe it's good to be here at Finland
where one of the tag lines has often
expected a miracle
we need one whoops
another bit friend of the community
Robert Gilman sketches it out in this
way he talks about the era the tribal
era that humanity went through and then
with the onset of Agriculture which to
some extent was also the onset of us
beginning to exploit the planet in a way
that wasn't very wise we became able to
settle and the era of empire started
started to build cities were started to
create nations and empires that went to
war against each other so we began a war
against nature and then we got began a
war against ourselves and then he Robert
speaks about this moving into what is
called the planetary era and what I like
about this graph is that in many ways
the the Renaissance seems
that with the Scientific Revolution a
new type of technology was made possible
that then made it possible to destroy
the planet much faster but at the same
time through science the same science
that gave us destructive technologies
also gave us an understanding of being
part of this living planet and this
transition out of the era of empire into
the planetary era to us with our 70 80
85 90 year life spans seems very sure
very long but really it's short for a
complete transformation of our
civilizational presence on earth and
that sometimes gives me hope that we're
now at the end of this large transition
area and that we just need to understand
that what seems like nothing is moving
is actually part of a larger process so
we are moving into the planetary era
this is me in 2006 just before I moved
to find' Han then the two big books in
my hand are volume 1 and volume 2 of
that PhD I mentioned earlier designed
for human and Planetary health a
holistic integral approach the
complexity and sustainability sounds
very academic what's amazing about this
is that that when I came to Finland I
like when I finished the PhD I couldn't
find any way to do postdoctoral research
because nobody wanted to fund me because
it was too transdisciplinary and it was
sent from one funding council to the
other and so I kind of put it in a
drawer came to find' Han where so some
extent I was in those days even it was
good to hide your PhD because there was
a bit of an attitude that if you had a
PhD you were in your head and therefore
you couldn't be in your heart and you
probably weren't spiritual and and it
took a while to here's a man who's lived
this for 50 years so I don't think it's
like that
but yeah just recently this summer I had
a phone call from a man who said
name's Anthony Capone I'm a professor at
the University of Sydney I'm in Europe
for a number of weeks because of two
conferences and in between those two
conferences I would really love to come
and see you and I said okay and that's
interesting yeah let's let's meet and so
he came to Majorca and he's the
co-author of a report that came out in
2017 by the Rockefeller Foundation and
The Lancet the top medical journal that
is called planetary health and this
whole mean that I wasn't actually aware
of because I stopped following it has
grown enormously in the last three four
or five years and there's a whole field
of medicine now that understands that
there's a deep link between eco systems
health and planetary health health
actually is and this comes from my PhD
is a emergent property of complex
dynamic systems at different levels of
scale so a healthy cell fits in a
healthy organ in a healthy body in a
healthy family in a healthy community in
a healthy bio region in a healthy
ecosystem on a healthy planet and of
course it goes the other way around if
we do anything that is unhealthy at any
of those levels it effects all other
levels I came to call planetary health
or I kept working in this field but a
couple of years ago I published a book
called designing regenerative cultures
because this idea of regeneration is
also about health the idea of resilience
is also about health and in this this
book that the title of this book also
kind of harbors a somewhat paradox which
is that I on the one hand we need to
redesign the human plasma presence on
earth and on the other hand cultures
aren't designed cultures emerge through
the interactions that we have with each
other the stories we tell so in that
sense
paradox I've learned from one of my
mentors at Omaha College that he said if
you step on a paradox you can be sure to
have some truth on your shoes life is
much more complicated than linear
either-or thinking so when we work with
paradoxes we get closer to what truth is
actually about and the other thing that
in writing the book I realized very
early on I thought what can I write in
this book that would actually be
meaningful in 10 years 15 years 20 years
time and at some point I realized most
of the solutions that human beings have
created for themselves and for future
generations
and were created with the best of
intentions and nevertheless so many of
them have turned into today's problems
so yesterday's solutions turn into
today's problems who are we to think
that our sustainable regenerative green
or whatever you want to call them
solutions will not turn into problems
later on so maybe we've got it wrong as
a culture that questions and transient
means to get to better answers and
better solutions but solutions and
answers are transient means to get to
better questions then maybe a wise
culture when you try to create a compass
that you can hand on from one generation
to the next would actually create a set
of questions to give to the next
generation how do we fit in who are we
obliged to why are we here where are we
going what is this all about
these questions need to find new ways of
meaning my my mentor David all once
floored me with the question of saying
Dan you before we can find the answer to
questions like how and what we might
have to do in order to create a
sustainable human presence on earth we
have to ask ourselves a much deeper
question and that question is what is it
about humanity that is worth sustaining
and if we find an answer to that
question then we might live our way into
the future in a wiser way
very briefly what do I mean by
regenerative this spectrum is from a
friend of mine called Bill Reid who
works with a group called the Regenesis
group it's also been influenced by a
woman called Carol Sanford and basically
it tells this it creates a spectrum from
business-as-usual to green which way
means doing things a little bit better
polluting a little less using a little
bit more renewable energy which is part
of the journey and then we get to
sustainable which means no negative
impacts like not adding any more damage
but because we've done so much damage we
need to do more than that so then you
move into restorative which can still be
in a mindset that is humanity as power
over nature and man and nature I'm
saying man on purpose because they've
created most of the mess and so you end
up with situations where we try to
create large forest plantations in the
wrong place of the wrong kind of species
and then then they like eucalyptus in a
water-stressed
area and they look very nice for a
decade or two and then they die because
we we engineered an ecosystem so once we
do the reconciliatory step shifting the
organizing idea that we are actually
nature that we can design as nature
because we're nothing but it we are
biological beings first and foremost
then we move into working regenerative
ly the oldest story of humanity is the
written story of humanity is the epic of
gilgamesh and it tells how the King
Gilgamesh was told by Humbaba the forest
thought that he was the old powerful
king but he wasn't allowed to cut down
the Cedars of Lebanon what did he do
Eragon won't say the word he ordered him
self Cedar Palace and killed him baba
and cut down the forest a modern
ecologist would call this downwind
desertification
home Baba's purse was if you cut down
the Cedars your rivers will run dry your
soil will go salty and your empire will
crumble and that's precisely what
happened and so we now face having to go
from this to this and it is possible
these are pictures from the Loess
Plateau in China Jim knew who was here a
conference documented this change over
14 years the Chinese managed to turn an
arid desert into a fertile and
productive landscape these are also all
images from that area and it's a very
large area here there's Beijing and this
is we're talking thousands of square
kilometers we can heal the planet we can
heal ecosystems we we can fit back into
the community of life and create
bioregion by bioregion a more abundant
place move from competitive scarcity to
share abundance this is a wonderful
image of a guy called Robert tzuke's who
who basically maps the river systems of
the planet and if we move into a bio
regional world if we start regenerating
bioregion by bio region this kind of map
is very useful because the the bio
regional approach is an approach that
fits humanity into natural patterns
rather than the other way around this
was a event that I helped to organize at
the Commonwealth and lady Patricia
Scotland from the she's she's the
Secretary General of the Commonwealth
and giving advice to 53 governments that
together rule the 2.4 billion people and
most of them under 30 and a lot of them
are in the frontline of climate change
and she's behind this idea of
regenerative development we brought key
practitioners of regenerative
development from all over the world
together and it's been a slow process in
terms of what's come out of that meeting
that was two years ago
but a lot of people met and started to
collaborate afterwards was directly come
out is this platform called common earth
that is giving advice to Commonwealth
countries on how to do regenerative
development and also showcasing best
practice examples there's an
organization in the Netherlands called
common land who's developed a strategy
of how to finance large-scale ecosystems
rest restoration and how to make it
viable and skip through this they the
common land has four
practice sites around the world where
they're working with regional land
owners to transform entire regions one
of them is the healthy plutonium musiah
in in Spain and John Liu the guy who
also did these images of the Loess
Plateau
has started an organization called
ecosystems restoration camp Foundation
which is basically inviting young people
or anybody from around the world to come
and learn how to be a restorer of
ecosystems in that place there's an
organization called the regen network
which are working on using remote
sensing satellite images and sensors on
the ground to really look at the before
after of regenerative work because once
you can quantify improve that you have
had a regenerative effect there are now
ways of finding funding link to that and
they're also working with new
cryptocurrencies to basically create
large funding streams into regenerative
practice these are just more images of
how they're doing it technically and
there's Peter head who used to run Arab
engineering that did a lot of the early
eco-cities he now runs an organization
called the resilience brokers and they
are starting next year on an ambitious
plan to by 2023 have worked with 200
city regions around the planet to build
resilience based on this shift towards a
more by original biomaterials economy
and the regenerate the regeneration of
ecosystems you've probably heard of the
book that Paul Hawken who lived some
years here at the
community or sometime he published this
book drawdown that lists a hundred
strategies of how to draw carbon out of
the atmosphere this is a lot beyond
carbon we shouldn't have carbon myopia
but right now we're faced with having to
stop runaway climate change and these
techniques are proven and governments
are now beginning to roll out programs
to work on this and this network by the
capital Institute that sets itself the
goal of region by region creating
regenerative economies as has just
launched last week
they're now seven Network seven regional
regeneration hopes of people working at
the bio regional scale to build by
regional biomaterial economies basically
shifting us out of carbon our entire
material culture is fossil fuel
dependent and we need to move into a new
type of material culture that is
biomaterial based in LOX carbon into
everything we use there's an
organization called regeneration
international that links farmers from
all over the world who practice
regenerative agriculture and the map
that this map shows where these
activities happen it's it's an
organization called well lush the
cosmetic companies runs the spring prize
that I have the honor to be on the jury
of and every February we meet to give
away two hundred thousand pounds to
organizations that do this work already
so there is some hope there is some
silver lining to the bad storm clouds
we're facing if you really want to stop
watching the bad news have a look at
this website from the button on saffle
Institute my friend David McConville
created a map that is a google map and
you can click on it and each point has a
little video of a story of people
actually doing regenerative work on the
ground and next year is the 50th
anniversary of Earth's rise the first
image from outer space of Earth rising
above moon it's also the 50th
anniversary of buckminster fuller's book
operation manual
they should earth and I think we're
getting closer to knowing what we need
to do and we're beginning to do it in
terms of Education I mentioned the
genesis of enough flicking through these
lights very fast em so just to close
this is a great teacher who has for
years
Gianna Macy's knowing that the key thing
that we need to change is upstream the
key thing that we need to change starts
in the human heart and the human
relationship with the earth and I love
what she says there is that like we've
been on the path of destroying this
planet for many many years probably
about 5,000 years since the beginning of
Agriculture but there's something
happening right now that we are
redefining our relationship to each
other to this planet and the potential
role of healing this planet and I'm
going to close with a poem that Jonah
Macy translated by one of my favorite
poets called Rainer Maria Rilke and it
speaks to our time it goes like this
deer darkening ground you have endured
so patiently the walls we've built maybe
you'll give the cities one more hour
cloisters and churches to and those who
labor maybe you'll let their work grip
them for another five hours or seven
until you become forests again and water
and widening wilderness in that hour of
inexplicable terror when you take back
your name from all things give me just a
little more time give me just a little
more time so I may love the things until
they're real and ripe and worthy of you
so invite you to all love life love the
opportunity of being alive we don't know
whether we're gonna make this we are
undergoing a species level right
of passage right now and rites of
passage mean that you you're not allowed
to know whether you're gonna make it
otherwise they don't work so we are
facing a knife's edge of a future that
is abundant of collaboration with nature
or decades of decline and unspeakable
unthinkable situations that we want to
avoid and the way to start navigating
the path towards the positive is to just
be in love with life and each other
every day a little bit more
[Applause]